Guide to the Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Historical Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- July 2005 Acquisitions, 1777-1920s; 7
  Research materials include engravings and clippings relating to Marie Antoinette.
  - Marie Antoinette, Queen, consort of Louis XVI, King of France (1755-1793)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Madame ma Soeur et Cousine la Reine de Sardaigne," concerning Comte de Viry, 1777 August (Box 8)
    - Manuscript document, signed, ordering the payment of 450 livres to Sieur de Salvert
    - Autograph letter, to "le comte," concerning court mourning, [1790 March 14] (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Mon Cousin le Cardinal Valenti", 1791 January 31 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Mon Cousin le Cardinal Gerdil", 1791 January 31 (Box 8)
    - Manuscript document, signed, to "Premier Maitre et Maitre ordinaire de Notre Hotel", 1791 January (Box 8)
    - Research Materials, 1920s, undated (Box 8)
  - Oversize
    - Manuscript document, signed, ordering the payment of 450 livres to Sieur de Salvert, 1783 July 1 (Box 11 Oversize)
- Other Acquisitions, 1569-1930; 4
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Name forms and dates of birth and death conform to Library of Congress authorities, except where indicated by brackets. Dates of accession are indicated on folders.
  - Browne, Hablot Knight (1815-1882). Drawings, pencil and watercolor, [circa 1839], [circa 1858] (Box 8)
    Drawings for Charles Dickens's Old Curiosity Shop, Library Edition, 1858 ("Dick Scriveller and the Marchioness" and "The Old Curiosity Shop"); and Nicholas Nickleby, 1839 edition ("Nicholas starts for Yorkshire")
  - Charles IX, King of France (1550-1574). Letter, signed, to M. de Helly, governor of Corbie, 1569 January 23 (Box 8)
  - Dickens, Charles (1812-1870). Autograph letter, signed, to Thomas Gaspey, [circa 1839] (Box 8)
  - Pearson, Eliphalet (1752-1826). Papers relating to Yale College, [circa 1800-1806] (Box 8)
    Manuscript copies in an undentified hand of 1701 and 1745 Yale College charters, with autograph manuscript notes by Pearson
  - [Saint-Mars, Benigne d'Auvergne de (d. 1708)]. Manuscript document, signed, 1699 June 10 (Box 8)
  - Wolfe, Humbert (1885-1940). Poem and letters, 1927-1930, undated (Box 8)
    Contents: "The Weasel", poem, typescript, corrected, signed; 11 typed and autograph letters, signed, to James Wells, 1927 February-1929 July; and 1 typed letter, signed, to Arthur Pforzheimer, 1930 May 28